听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
我想讨论的第二个思想实验叫
The second thought experiment that I want to discuss is called
拜占庭将军问题
the Byzantine generals problem.
在我讲解具体内容之前
Before I get into the details,
我们先来讨论一下发音问题 到底是“ˈbɪzəntiːn”还是“baɪˈzæntaɪn”
a question of pronunciation is it “ˈbɪzəntiːn” or “baɪˈzæntaɪn” generals?
据我所知
Well, so, as far as I know,
标准英式英语的发音是“baɪˈzæntaɪn”
the standard British pronunciation of this word is actually “baɪˈzæntaɪn”,
而“ˈbɪzəntiːn”是美式英语发音
and “ˈbɪzəntiːn” is the American pronunciation.
然而 在计算机领域 大部分人的读音是“bɪzənˈtiːn”
However, in computing, it seems to be most common to use “bɪzənˈtiːn”.
因此 我这里也遵从习俗 把这个词发音为“bɪzənˈtiːn”
And so, I'm just going to stick with the pronunciation “bɪzənˈtiːn”,
因为这也是计算机领域其他人常使用的发音
because that's what everyone else in computing seems to do.
拜占庭将军问题乍看起来与两将军问题很相似
So, the Byzantine generals problem is similar at first glance to the two generals problem,
这也是以将军率领军队打仗为背景描述的问题
that is, again, we've got generals leading armies,
军队同样希望进攻一个城市
again, the armies want to attack a city.
在这个问题中 我们可能会有三支或者更多支军队
In this case, we might have three or more armies.
我们有多支军队
We might have any number of armies.
和之前一样 将军通过信使完成通信
As before, the generals communicate by messenger.
同样 军队需要商议出进攻日期
And as before, the armies want to agree on the date of attack
保证军队可以同时发起进攻
so that to ensure that they attack at the same time.
现在 我们在某个方面把问题简单化 但在另一个方面把问题复杂化
Now, we make the problem easier in one way and harder in another way.
简单化的部分如下 首先 我们假设消息通信过程是可靠的
So, easier, first of all, is we assume that messaging is reliable.
在这个问题中 我们假设信使不会被抓获
So, in this case, we're going to assume messengers don't get captured,
任何发送出去的消息一定会被相应的接收方所接收
but any message that gets sent will actually be received by the appropriate recipient.
复杂化的地方是 我们现在假设
To make the problem harder, we are now going to assume that
有些将军是不忠诚的 他们是背叛者 他们是恶意的
some of the generals are actually not loyal. They are traitors. They are malicious.
他们会尝试主动陷害其他将军
They are going to try to actively undermine the other generals.
他们会撒谎 会欺骗
So, they are going to lie and deceive,
他们会按照任何他们期望的形式作出不端的行动
and generally misbehave in any sort of way as they wish.
他们甚至可能会共谋
They might even work together.
尽管如此 我们仍然希望
And nevertheless, we want
诚实的将军们可以协商出向城市发起进攻的时间
the honest generals to come to an agreement about the attack of the city.
让我通过一个例子来说明
So, let me give an example of the problem that might arise
当存在恶意将军时 会出现什么问题
due to some generals being malicious.
具体例子如下 将军1向将军2和将军3发送消息“进攻！”
So, here, in this example, general 1 sends a message “Attack!” to generals 2 and 3,
给两位将军发送的消息都是“进攻！”
the same message “Attack!”.
将军3如愿收到了消息
And general 3 receives that message as expected.
将军2收到了进攻消息
General 2 receives the attack message,
他随后给将军3发送一条消息称“将军1说撤退！”
and then sends a message to general 3 saying “Retreat!”.
将军2这里做的事情就是说谎
So, what general 2 here is doing is lying.
将军2称将军1发送了一条撤退消息
General 2 claims that general 1 sent a retreat message
但实际上 将军1发送了一条进攻消息
when in fact, general 1 sent an attack message.
因此 在这种情况下 将军2实施了恶意行为
So, in this case, here, general 2 is the one who is being malicious.
不幸的是 从将军3的视角上看 他很难判断出到底发生了什么
Unfortunately, from the point of general 3, it's not easy to tell what is actually happening
因为从将军3的视角上看
because from the point of general 3,
也有可能发生的是下图所描述的情况
what could have just this equally well happened is this one.
有可能是将军1向将军3发送了一条进攻消息
So, it could be that general 1 sent an attack message to 3.
而将军1向将军2发送了一条撤退消息
And general 1 sent a retreat message to 2.
实际上
And general 2 is actually
将军2诚实地重复了将军1发来的撤退消息
faithfully repeating that retreat message that it got from general 1.
在下图所示的情况下 将军2才是诚实的
So, in this case, in the lower case here, general 2 is being honest,
因为将军2只是诚实报告了将军1发来的消息
because general 2 is just reporting honestly what general 1 said.
将军1实施了恶意行为
And it's general 1 who is being malicious
将军1向将军2和将军3发送了相互矛盾的命令
by sending contradictory commands to generals 2 and 3.
在将军3的视角下 我们面对的核心问题是
So, the core of the problem here from the point of view of general 3 is
将军3无法区分这两个场景
it's impossible to tell the difference between these two scenarios.
将军3无法知道
And so, it's impossible for general 3 to tell
到底是将军1作恶 还是将军2作恶
whether general 1 is being malicious or whether general 2 is.
正如我前面所说 在节点可能说谎的场景下
Now, given this scenario where nodes might lie,
拜占庭将军问题所要达成的目标是
the Byzantine generals problem is that
我们希望所有诚实的将军可以达成一致
we want all of the honest generals to come to an agreement.
现在 我们面对的问题是
So now, the problem is that
诚实的将军无法知道恶意将军会做些什么
the honest generals don't know who the malicious generals are.
但我们可以假设恶意将军的数量不会超过某个最大值
But we are going to assume some maximum number of generals being malicious.
我们可以假设 一共有n位将军 其中最多有f位将军是恶意的
So, let's say that up to f generals are malicious out of n generals in total.
诚实将军不知道哪些人是恶意将军
The honest generals don't know who the malicious ones are,
但恶意将军知道其他恶意将军是谁
but the malicious generals may know who the other malicious generals are.
因此 他们甚至可以共同协作
And so, they might actually even work together in some coordinated fashion
尝试欺骗和愚弄诚实将军
to try to deceive and trick the honest generals.
尽管如此 我们要求诚实将军仍然可以协商出一个计划
And nevertheless, our requirement is that the honest generals agree on a plan.
我们不能约束恶意将军必须使用某种计划来作恶
So, we can't get the malicious generals to agree on any part of the plan
因为我们假设恶意将军可以按照任意的方法实施恶意行为
because we're assuming that they might misbehave in arbitrary ways.
因此 我们不可能知道他们会按照什么策略实施恶意行为
And so, it's impossible for us to make any statement about what they are going to do,
但我们可以允许让诚实将军按照一定的策略行动
but we can make a statement about what the honest generals are going to do.
而最终的目的是让诚实将军可以在相同日期发起进攻
And that is, what we want them to do is to all attack on the same day.
根据问题启动时所面对的不同情况
Now, there are several different variants of the Byzantine generals problem
可以构造出拜占庭将军问题的很多变种问题
that vary in the details of how exactly it's set up.
但对于一些变种问题 我们可以证明出一个通用结论
But a typical result that we can prove about some of these variants is that
如果我们最多有f位恶意将军
if we have a maximum of f malicious generals,
则我们总共至少需要3f+1位将军
then we need at least 3f+1 generals in total
才能容忍f位将军实施恶意行为
in order to tolerate those f generals being malicious,
也就是说 恶意将军的数量必须小于将军总数量的1/3
that is, less than 1/3 of the total number of generals can be malicious.
如果我们有3位将军 其中1位将军是恶意的 则此问题无解
So, if we have 3 generals, and 1 is malicious, the problem is unsolvable.
为了能让系统容忍1位恶意将军 我们至少需要4位将军
In order to tolerate a system with 1 malicious general, we need at least 4,
也就是说 当f=1时 我们总计至少需要4位将军
that is, f=1, we need at least 4 generals in total.
3位是诚实的 1位是恶意的
So, 3 honest ones and 1 malicious.
如果我们希望系统中包含2位可能的恶意将军
If we want a system in which 2 generals might be malicious,
我们总计需要7位将军 5位诚实将军 2位恶意将军
we actually need 7, so, 5 honest and 2 malicious generals.
如果假定我们可以使用密码学技术 则这个问题会相对简单一些
Now, the problem becomes somewhat easier if we assume that we can use cryptography.
我不会在这门课程中讲解用具体怎么使用密码学解决此问题
And so, I won't go into the details of that in this course.
在下一年的安全课程和密码学课程中
There's more detail on this in the security course and in the cryptography course
大家会了解具体细节
that you will have next year.
简述一下大致的方法 我们可以使用一个叫数字签名的技术
But what we can do here is use something called a digital signature,
这是一种消息形式 此消息形式可以证明
which is a form of message in which it can be proved that
特定的消息一定是特定的参与方发送的
a certain party sent a certain message.
来看前面我给出的例子
And so, in this case, for example,
数字签名允许将军2向将军3证明
it would allow general 2 to prove what a command general 1 sent to general 2,
我发送的就是将军1发送给将军2的消息
and prove that to general 3 in a way that
这样一来 将军3会相信将军2是诚实的
general 3 would be convinced that general 2 really is honest.
密码学会提供一定的帮助
So, cryptography does help,
但密码学无法让拜占庭将军问题变成一个简单问题
but it doesn't make the Byzantine generals problems magically simple.
即使假定我们可以使用密码学 拜占庭将军问题仍然是一个很困难的问题
So, even if we do assume that we can use cryptography, the problem remains difficult.
你可能会问：这个问题和实际场景有什么联系吗？
So, is this at all of practical relevance? You might ask.
我们把这个问题引入到前面已经多次提到的一个实际问题中
So, let's adapt this earlier example that we've had a few times now
即引入到在线商店和支付服务问题
of the online shop and the payment service.
在这个场景下 我们让客户作为第三个参与方
And let's take, in this case, the customer as a third party in this.
这样一来 我们就在商店、支付服务、客户之间
So, we have this kind of three-way relationship
构建了一个三角关系
between the shop, the payment service, and the customer.
我们希望这三个参与方
And we want all three of these parties
可以对交易状态或订单状态达成一致
to agree on the status of a transaction, or the status of an order.
我们希望在线商店发货之前已经确认
So, we want the online shop to ship the goods only if
支付服务已经处理完了支付过程
it agrees with the payment service that the payment actually happened,
且客户已经为商品下单
and if the customer actually agreed that they did actually order this thing,
客户希望确认自己确实用信用卡支付了约定好的金额 等等
and the customer agrees on the amount that was charged the card, and so on.
因此 所有参与方都需要达成一致
So, all of these parties need to agree.
在实际生活中
And in real life,
三个参与方的信任关系可能会变得非常复杂
the trust relationships between these three parties might be quite complicated.
如果从在线商店的角度考虑这个问题
So, if you think about it from the perspective of the online shop,
如果存在某种方法
if there was some way
使客户可以在不需要支付费用的条件下购买商品
how people could order goods from an online shop without paying for them,
你可以想象到 骗子们就会趋之若鹜
you can imagine that fraudsters would be using that pretty quickly,
他们会在不完成支付的前提下 给所有昂贵的商品下单
and they would be ordering all sorts of expensive things without paying for them.
在线商店不希望发生这样的事情
And so, the online shop would not be happy then.
因此 从在线商店的角度看
So, from the point of view of the online shop,
在线商店需要假定客户可能存在恶意行为
the customer needs to be treated as potentially malicious,
因为如果盲目信任客户
because if the customer was just blindly trusted,
那客户就可以实施上述欺骗行为
then they might start doing fraudulent activity like that.
因此 在线商店和客户之间存在不信任的关系
So, in that case, we do have this kind of untrusting relationship.
在线商店和支付服务的信任关系又如何呢？
What about the online shop and the payment service, the relationship?
你可以想象到 支付服务可能不那么信任在线商店
Well, you can imagine maybe the payment service doesn't quite trust the online shop,
否则 某些人可能会开设一个诈骗在线商店
because otherwise, someone might set up a fraudulent online shop,
用偷来的信用卡号码尝试交易
use, say, stolen credit card numbers, to try and process transactions
在不发送任何商品的条件下收钱
and get money without actually shipping any real goods.
在这种情况下 可能支付服务不能完全信任在线商店
So, in that case, probably the payment service doesn't fully trust the online shop.
但在线商店可能会信任支付服务
But maybe the shop does trust the payment service.
因此 这里还存在非平衡的信任关系
So, it might be this kind of asymmetric relationship.
正如大家所看到的 现实生活中的信任关系可能会非常复杂
So, as you can see here, the trust relationships in real life get rather complicated.
很多场景下都会出现一个参与方不信任另一个参与方的情况
You do end up in these situations where one party does not trust another party.
尽管如此 他们仍然希望一起搞定某些事情
And they nevertheless want to get something done.
因此 从这个角度看 拜占庭行为在现实中是真实存在的
And so, in that sense, Byzantine behavior is real and practical.
很显然 拜占庭将军问题对此类场景进行了高度的简化
The Byzantine generals problem is of course a simplification of this kind of scenario,
举例来说 拜占庭将军问题认为所有将军的信任关系是平等的
because it's treating all of the generals as symmetric, for example.
尽管是一个简化版问题 拜占庭将军问题仍然是一个很好的出发点
But nevertheless, the Byzantine generals problem is a useful starting point
用于研究参与方不能相互信任的一类场景
for studying these kind of situations in which the participants don't fully trust each other.
在我结束拜占庭将军问题的介绍之前
So, before I wrap up about the Byzantine generals problem,
我还想讲个和历史相关的题外话
one more little historical digression,
你可能会好奇 为什么把这个问题称为“拜占庭”将军问题？
you might be wondering where the name Byzantine comes from.
这个问题来自于拜占庭帝国
So, this comes from the Byzantine empire,
拜占庭帝国也称东罗马帝国
which also known as Byzantium, the former east Roman empire,
拜占庭帝国是罗马帝国覆灭后东侧部分所形成的帝国
which after the collapse of the Roman empire, this was the eastern part of it.
拜占庭帝国的首都是君士坦丁堡 这个城市之前就叫拜占庭
And its capital city was Constantinople, which was formerly known as Byzantium,
这个城市现在是位于土耳其的伊斯坦布尔
which is now where Istanbul is located in Turkey.
在二十世纪初 出于某些原因
And so, for some reason in the early 20th century,
人们开始用“拜占庭”这个术语
I think the term Byzantine became used
来描述极为复杂的场景
in order to describe scenarios where things are excessively complicated
或者描述非常官僚的场景 乃至潜在的不正当问题
or incredibly bureaucratic, or potentially even devious,
例如用来描述税收立法等事件
for example, tax legislation or these kind of thing.
目前还不完全清楚为什么会使用“拜占庭”这个术语描述此类问题
Not entirely sure why that meaning of Byzantine occurred
因为没有历史证据表明
because there's no historical evidence really that
拜占庭帝国与其他帝国相比有过更恶意或者更诚实的行为
the Byzantine empire was any more or less malicious than any other empire.
不管怎样 这就是“拜占庭”这个术语的由来
But anyway, that's where it came from.
人们很早就开始使用“拜占庭”这个术语了
So, the term Byzantine had this meaning
在计算机领域引入这个术语之前 人们就开始使用“拜占庭”这个术语了
long before it was used in the context of computing.
因此 使用“拜占庭”与计算机领域无关
So, it is outside of computing.
人们早就开始使用“拜占庭”这个术语了
It has had that meaning for a long time.
这就是拜占庭将军问题的全部内容
So, that's all on the Byzantine generals problem for now.